PROFESSOR: All right.
Let's get started.
Welcome, ladies and gentlemen.
Today it's my pleasure to
introduce two guest speakers
who will talk about
the regulation of AI
and machine learning and about
both the federal FDA level
regulation and about
IRB issues of regulation
within institutions.
So the first speaker
is Andy Coravos.
Andy is the CEO and founder
of Elektra Labs, which
is a small company that's doing
digital biomarkers for health
care.
And Mark is a data
and software engineer
for the Institute for Next
Generation Healthcare at Mount
Sinai in New York
and was kind enough
to come up to speak to us today.
So with that, I'm
going to introduce them
and sit back and enjoy.
ANDY CORAVOS: Thank you.
Thank you for having us.
Yeah, so I am working
on digital biomarkers,
and I'm also a research
collaborator at the Harvard MIT
Center for Regulatory Sciences.
So you all have a center
that is looking just
at how regulators should think
about some of these problems.
And then I'm also an
advisor at the Biohacking
Village at DEFCON, which we can
talk a little bit more about.
My background-- I'm
a software engineer,
had worked with the FDA formerly
as an entrepreneur resident
in the digital health unit,
and then spent some time
in corporate land.
MARK SHERVEY: I'm Mark Shervey.
I work at the Institute for
Next Generation Healthcare
at Mount Sinai.
I've been there about
three years now.
My background is in software
and data engineering,
coming mostly from
banking and media.
So this is a new spot.
And most of my
responsibilities focus around
data security and IRB and
ethical responsibilities.
ANDY CORAVOS: We also know
how much people generally
love regulatory
conversations, so we
will try to make this very
fun and exciting for you.
If you do have questions,
as regulations are weird
and they're constantly
changing, you can also
shoot us a note on Twitter.
We'll respond back if you
have things that come up.
Also, the regulatory
community on Twitter, amazing.
When somebody comes
out with, like,
what does real world
data actually mean,
everybody is talking
to one another.
So once you start tapping into--
I'm sure you have your
own Twitter communities,
but if you tap into the
regulatory Twitter community,
it is a very good one.
The digital health unit
tweets a lot at the FDA.
OK.
Disclaimers-- these are our
opinions and the information
that you'll see here
does not necessarily
reflect the United States
government or the institutions
that we are affiliated with.
And policies and regulations
are constantly changing.
So by the time we have
presented this to you,
most likely parts
of it are wrong.
So you should definitely
interact early and often
with relevant
regulatory institutions.
Your lawyers might
say not to do that.
There are definitely
different ways,
and we can talk through
how you'd want to do that.
But especially as a software
engineer and developing
anything on the
data side, if you
spend too much time developing
a product that is never
going to get through, it is
really a wasted period of time.
So working with the
regulators, and given
how open they are right
now to getting feedback,
as you saw with the
paper that you read,
is going to be important.
And then the last thing, which
Mark and I talk a lot about,
is many of these definitions
and frameworks have not actually
happened yet.
And so when somebody
says a biomarker,
they might actually
not mean a biomarker,
they might mean a measurement.
I'm sure you know this.
When someone's like, I work
in AI, and you're like,
what does that actually mean?
So you should ask us questions.
And if you think about it, the
type of knowledge that you have
is a very specific, rare set
of knowledge compared to almost
everybody else in the country.
And so as the FDA
and other regulators
start thinking about how
to regulate and oversee
these technologies, you can
have a really big amount
of influence.
And so what we're going
to do is a little bit
of the dry stuff
around regulatory,
and then I am going to
somewhat plead with you
and also teach you how to submit
public comments so that you
can be part of this
regulatory process.
And then--
MARK SHERVEY: I will speak about
the Institutional Review Board.
How many people in here
have worked with an IRB
or aware of them?
OK, good.
That's a good mix.
So it'll be a quick
thing, just kind
of reviewing when
to involve the IRB,
how to involve the
IRB, things you
need the IRB for and
some things that you
don't, as an alternative
to taking the FDA approach.
ANDY CORAVOS: All right, good.
And then I'll go first, and
then we'll go through IRBs,
and then we'll leave the last
part for your impressions
of the paper.
OK.
So before I start,
I'll ground us
in some ideas around
algorithmically-driven health
care products.
So as you know, these
can have wide ranges
of what they can do.
A general framework that I
like to use to think about them
is products that measure,
that diagnose, or treat.
So measurement products
might include things
like digital biomarkers or
clinical decision support.
Diagnostics might take that
measurement and then say
whether or not somebody
has some sort of condition
given those metrics.
And then treatment are ideas
around digital therapeutics.
How many people here think that
software can treat a person?
A few, maybe.
OK.
And I think one thing that
people don't think about always
when they have these
sorts of tools is--
and you all probably think
about this a lot more--
is even something as simple as
a step count is an algorithm.
So it takes your gyroscope,
accelerometer, height, weight,
and age, and then it
predicts whether or not
you've made a step.
And if you think about the
types of different steps
that people make, older
people drag their feet
a little bit more
than younger people.
So an algorithm for
a step count looks
very different from an algorithm
for younger people for step
count.
And so all of these tools
have some level of error,
and they're all
algorithms, effectively.
One of my favorite frameworks
as you start thinking about--
a lot of people are very
interested in the measurement
side around what's called
digital biomarkers.
And it turns out
that the FDA realized
that many people, even
within their own agency,
didn't know what
a biomarker was,
and everyone was using the
term slightly differently,
probably how people approach
you slightly differently of what
machine learning actually is.
And so there is a
really good framework
around the seven different
types of biomarkers
that I'd highly recommend you
read if you go into this area.
A digital biomarker
only, in my definition
and how other people
have started to use this,
is the way that that
measurement is collected.
And so you might have
a monitoring biomarker,
a diagnostic
biomarker, but it is
collected in an
ambulatory, remote way that
is collecting digital data.
And this type of
data is very tricky.
To give you an example of why
this is particularly difficult
to regulate, so
think about a couple
of products that just
look at something that
would be simple, like AFib.
So AFib is an abnormal
heart condition.
You might have seen in
the news that a number
of different companies are
coming out with AFib products.
Put simply, there is
obviously a large stack
of different types of data,
and one person's raw data
is another person's
processed data.
So what you see on
this chart is a list
of five different
companies that are all
developing AFib products,
from whether or not
they develop the
product internally,
which is the green part,
versus whether or not
they might use a third
party product, so developing
an app on top of
somebody else's product.
And so in a broad way, thinking
about going from the operating
system to the sensor data.
So somebody might be using
something like a PPG sensor
and collecting this sort
of data from their watch
and then doing some sort
of signal processing,
then making another
algorithm that
makes some sort of diagnostic.
And then you have some sort of
user interface on top of that.
So if you are the FDA, where
would you draw the line?
Which part of this
product, when somebody
says my product is
validated, should it
be actually validated?
And then thinking
about what does
it actually mean if something
is verified versus validated.
So verified being like,
if I walk 100 steps,
does this thing
measure 100 steps?
And then validation
being, does 100 steps
mean something for
my patient population
or for my clinical use case?
And so one of the things
that the FDA has started
to think through is how might
you decouple the hardware
components from the
software components, where
you think about some of the
hardware components as the ways
that you would--
effectively, the supply chain
for collecting that data,
and then you would be
using something on top.
And so maybe you
have certain types
of companies that might do
some sort of verification
or validation lower
down the stack,
and then you can
innovate higher up.
And so these measurements have
pretty meaningful impacts.
So in the past, a
lot of these tools,
you really had to
go into the clinic.
It was very expensive to get
these sorts of measurements.
And more and more, a number
of different companies
are getting their
products cleared
to use in some care
settings with a doctor
or possibly to inform
decisions at home.
All right.
And so in the last
of some examples
is around digital therapeutics.
So I had worked
with a company that
was using a technology based
out of UCSF that is developing,
effectively, a video
game for pediatric ADHD.
And so when kids
play the game, they
reduce their ADHD symptoms.
And one of things that's pretty
exciting about this game it
is a 30-day protocol.
And unlike something
like Ritalin or Adderall,
where you have to take
that drug every day
for the rest of your life
as you reduce the symptoms,
this seems to have an
effect that, after 30 days,
is more long-term and that when
you test somebody months down
the line, they still retain
the effects of the treatment.
So this technology
was taken out of UCSF
and licensed to a company
called Akili, who decided, hey,
we should just structure
ourselves like a drug company.
So they raised venture
capital like a drug company,
they ran clinical trials
like a drug company,
and they're now
submitting to the FDA
and might be the first
prescription drug.
So anybody who was told
that video games might
rot your brain, you now
have a revenge, maybe.
So the FDA has been looking at
more and more of these tools.
I don't have to tell
you, you're probably
thinking a lot about it.
And the FDA has been clearing a
number of these different types
of algorithms.
And one of the questions
that has come up
is, what part of the agency
should you think about?
What are you claiming when you
use these sorts of algorithms?
And what ones should be
cleared and what's not?
And how should we really think
about the regulatory oversight
for them?
And a lot of these
technologies enable things that
are really quite exciting, too.
So it's not just
about the measurement,
but what you can do with them.
So one thing that has a lot
of people really excited about
is an idea around
decentralized clinical trials.
No block chains here.
You might be able to build
it with a blockchain,
but not necessary.
So on the y-axis, you
can think about where
are the data collected.
So is it collected
at a clinical site,
or is it collected remotely?
And then the method
is how it's collected.
So do you need a human
to do the interaction,
or is it fully virtual?
So at the top you can
think about somebody
doing telemedicine, where they
call into somebody at home
and then they might
ask some questions
and fill out a survey.
On the bottom, you can
imagine in a research facility
where I'm using a number
of different instruments,
and perhaps I'm in
a Parkinson's study
and you're measuring my
tremor with some sort
of accelerometer.
And so the challenge that's
happening is a lot of people
use all of these terms
for different things
when they mean
decentralized trials.
Is it telemedicine?
Is it somebody
who's instrumented
with a lot of wearables?
How do you know that
the data are accurate?
But this is, I think, in many
instances really exciting
because the number
one reason why
people don't want to
enroll in a clinical trial
is to get a placebo.
I think nobody really
wants to participate
in research if you're not
getting the actual drug.
And then the other
reason is location.
People don't want to
have to drive in, find
parking, participate.
And this allows people
to participate from home.
And the FDA has been
doing a lot of work
around how to rethink the
clinical trial design process
and incorporate some
of this real world data
into decision-making.
Before I jump into some
of the regulatory things,
I want to just set a
framework of how to think
about what these tools can do.
So these are three
different scenarios
of how you might use software
in a piece of clinical research.
So imagine that somebody
has Parkinson's and you
want to measure how
their Parkinson's is
changing over time using
a smartphone-based test.
You have a standard Parkinson's
drug that they would use,
and then you would collect
the endpoint data, which
is how you see if that
drug has performed
using a piece of software.
Another idea would be, say
you have an insulin pump
and then you have a CGM that
is measuring your blood sugar
levels, and you want to
dose the insulin based
on those readings.
You might have software both
on the interventional side
and on the endpoint side.
Or, like the company
we talked about,
which has a digital
product, they
said the only thing we
want to change in the study
is that the
intervention is digital,
but we want you to compare us
like any other intervention
for pediatric ADHD.
So we want to use
standard endpoints
and not make that an innovation.
The challenge here is the
first one, most likely,
would go to the drug
side of the FDA.
The second one would go to
both the drug and the device
side of the FDA as a
combination product.
And the final one would
just go to devices,
which has been generally
handling software.
We've never really had products
at the FDA, in my opinion,
where--
we don't have drugs that
can measure, diagnose,
and treat and change
all the different ways.
And so you're now
having software
hitting multiple different
parts of a system,
or it might even be the same
product, but in one instance
it's used as an intervention,
another instance it's
used as a diagnostic,
another it's
to inform or expand labeling.
And so the lines are
not as clean anymore
about how you would
manage this product.
So how do you manage these?
There's a couple
agencies that are
responsible for thinking through
and overseeing health care
software.
The big one that we'll spend
most of our time on is the FDA.
But it's also worth
thinking about how
they interact with
some of the other ones,
including ONC, FCC, and FTC.
So the FDA is responsible
for safety and effectiveness
and for facilitating
medical product innovation
and ensuring that
patients have access
to high quality products.
The ONC is responsible for
health information technology.
And you can imagine where the
lines between storing data
and whether or not you're making
a diagnosis on that data start
to get really
vague, and it really
might be the exact
same product but just
the change of what claim
you're making on that product.
And most of these products
have some level of connectivity
to them, so they also
are working with FCC
and have to abide by the ways
that these tools are regulated
by this agency.
And then finally, and
probably most interesting,
is around the FTC,
which is really focused
on informing consumer choice.
And if you think
about FDA and FTC,
they're actually really similar.
So both of these agencies
are responsible for consumer
protection, and the FDA really
takes that with a public health
perspective.
So in many instances, if you've
seen some of the penalties
around somebody having
deceptive practices,
it actually wasn't the FDA who
stepped in, it was the FTC.
And I think some
of the agencies are
thinking about where
do their lines end
and where do others begin.
And in many instances,
as we've really
seen with a lot of probably bad
behavior that happens in tech,
there's really gaps
across multiple places
where nobody's stepping in.
And then there's some also
non-regulatory agencies
to think about.
An important one is around
standards and technology.
You probably think
about this all the time
with interoperability
and whether
or not you can actually
import the data.
There are people who
spend a lot of time
thinking about standards.
It is a very painful
and very important
job to promote innovation.
OK.
So the FDA has multiple centers.
I'm going to use
a lot of acronyms,
so you might want to write
this down or take a picture.
And I'll try to
minimize my acronyms.
But there are three centers that
will be the most interesting
for you.
So CDER is the one
for drugs, and this
is the one where you
would have a regular drug
and possibly use a
software product to see
how that drug is performing.
CDHR is for devices.
And CBER is for
biological products.
I will probably use
drugs and biologics
in a very similar sort of way.
And the distinctions that
we'll spend most of our time on
are around drugs versus device.
There's a bunch
of policy that is
coming out that is both exciting
and making things change.
So one of the big ones is
around the 21st Century Cures.
This has accelerated a lot
of innovation in health care.
It's also changed the
definition of what device is,
which has a pretty meaningful
impact on software.
And the FDA has
been thinking a lot
about how you would actually
incorporate these products in.
I think there is a
lot of people who
are really excited about them.
There's a lot of
innovation, and so how
do we create standards
both to expand labeling,
be able to actually
ingest digital data,
and have these sorts
of digital products
that are actually
under FDA oversight
and not just weird snake
oil on the app store?
But what is a medical device?
Pretty much, a device
is like anything
that's not the
other centers, which
has a big catch-all for
all the other components.
And so one of the big
challenges for people
is thinking about
what a device is.
If you think about
generally what the FDA does,
it doesn't always make
sure that your products
are safe and effective.
They check whether or
not you claim that they
are safe and effective.
So it's really all
about claims management
and what you're claiming
that this product can do
and evaluating
that for marketing.
Obviously if your product
causes very significant harm,
that is an issue.
But the challenge really happens
to be when somebody makes--
the product can do something
that it doesn't necessarily
claim to do, but then
you are able to imply
that it does other things.
Most people don't really have
a really good understanding
of what the difference
is between informing
a product versus
diagnosing a product,
and so I think in many
instances for the public,
it gets a bit confusing.
So as we talked
about before, the FDA
has been thinking
about how do you
decouple the hardware
from the software,
and they've come up with
a concept around software
as a medical device,
so the software
that is effectively defined
as having no hardware
components where you can
evaluate just this product,
and this is pronounced SaMD.
And SaMDs are
pretty interesting.
This is very hard to
read, but I pulled it
straight from legal
documents, so you
know I'm not changing it.
So something that's
interesting about SaMD--
so if you go all
the way to the end--
so if you have electronic health
care data that's just storing
health data, that is
not a SaMD and often
can go straight to market and
is not regulated by the FDA.
If you have a piece of software
that is embedded into a system,
so something like a pacemaker
or a blood infusion pump,
then that is software
in a medical device,
and that's not a SaMD.
So there's a line between these
about what the functionality is
that the product is doing,
and then how serious is it,
and that informs how you would
be evaluated for that product.
And if you haven't noticed,
I try not to almost ever use
the term device.
So when I talked about
these connected wearables
and other sorts of tools, I
will use the word tool and not
device because this has a very
specific meaning for the FDA.
And so if you're curious whether
or not your product is a device
or your algorithm is
a device, first, you
should talk to the regulators
and talk to your lawyer.
And we'll play a little game.
So there are two products here.
One is an Apple product and
one is a Fitbit product.
Which one is a device?
I'm going to call on
somebody randomly,
or someone can raise their
hand and offer as tribute.
OK, which one?
AUDIENCE: I think Apple
received 510(k) clearance,
so I'd say the
Apple Watch device.
I'm not sure about the Fitbit,
but if it's one or the other,
then it's probably not.
ANDY CORAVOS: That's very sharp.
So we'll talk about this.
Apple did submit to
the FDA for clearance,
and they submitted
for de novo, which
is very similar to a 510(k).
And they submitted for
two products, two SaMDs.
One was based on the
signal from their PPG,
and the second was on the app.
So it has two devices,
neither of which are hardware.
And the Fitbit has,
today, no devices.
How about now?
Is it a device, or
is it not a device?
Trick question,
obviously, because there
are two devices there,
and then a number
of things that are not devices.
So it really just
depends on what you
are claiming the product does.
And back to that
set of modularity,
what is actually the product?
So is the product a signal
processing algorithm?
Is the product an app?
Is the product the
whole entire system?
And so people are
thinking about,
strategically,
frankly, which parts
are devices because you might
want somebody else to be
building on your system.
So maybe you want to make
your hardware a device,
and then other people
can build off of it.
And so there are strategic
ways of thinking about it.
So the crazy thing here,
if you can imagine this,
is that the exact same product
can be a device or not a device
through just a change of words
and no change in hardware
or code.
So if you think about whether
or not my product is a device,
it's actually generally not
the most useful question.
The more useful question
is, what is the intended use
of the product?
And so, are you making a
medical device claim with what
your product is doing?
Obviously this is a
little bit overwhelming,
I think, in trying to figure
out how to navigate all of this.
And the FDA recognizes
that, and their goal
is to increase innovation.
And so particularly for
products like software, they're
having constant updates.
It seems a little bit
difficult if you're constantly
figuring out all
the different words
and how you're going to get
these products to market.
So something that I think is
really innovative by the FDA
is piloting--
this is one example of a program
that they're thinking through,
which is working with
nine different companies.
And the idea is, can you
pre-certify an entire company
that is developing software
as an excellent company
across a series of
objectives, and then
allow them to ship
additional updates?
So today, if you had
an update and you
wanted to make a
change, you have
to go through an entire
510(k) or de novo process
or other type of process,
which is pretty wild.
If you imagine
that we only would
let Facebook ship one update
a year, that would be crazy.
And we don't expect Facebook
to maintain or sustain
a human life.
And so being able
to have updates
in a more regular fashion
is very important.
But how do you know that
that change is going
to have a big impact or not?
And I'll pause on this, but
you all read the document.
I'm actually very glad
that you read this document
without talking to us because
you were the exact audience
of somebody who
would not necessarily
have the background,
and so it needs
to be put in a way that
is readable for people who
are developing these
types of products
to know how to go into them.
We'll save some time at
the end of the discussion
because I'm curious how
you perceived the piece.
But you should definitely
trust your first reading
as a honest, good reading.
You also probably read
it way more intensely
than any other person
who is reading it,
and so the notes that
you took are valid.
And I'm curious what you saw.
OK.
Another thing to help you
be cool at cocktail hour.
FDA cleared, not the same
thing as FDA approved.
OK.
So for devices, there are
three pathways to think about.
One is the 510(k),
the next is de novo,
the next is a premarket
approval, also known as a PMA.
They're generally
stratified by whether or not
something is risky.
And the type of
data that you have
to submit to be able to get
one of these clearances varies.
So the more risky you
are, the more type
of data that you have to have.
So de novos are granted, but
people often will say cleared.
510(k)s are cleared.
Very few products that you've
seen go through a PMA process.
AUDIENCE: I have a question.
ANDY CORAVOS: Tell me.
AUDIENCE: Do you know
why Apple chose to do
a de novo instead of a 510(k)?
ANDY CORAVOS: I am not
Apple, but if I had to guess,
once you create a de
novo, you can then become
a predicate for other things.
And so if they wanted to create
a new class of predicates
that they could then
build on over time,
and they didn't
want to get stuck
in an old type of
predicate system,
I think, strategically,
the fact that they
picked a PPG and their app--
I don't know what they'll
eventually do over time,
but I think it's part of
their long-term strategy.
Great question.
OK.
So the tools are safe
and effective, perhaps,
depending on how much
data is submitted.
But what about the
information that's
collected from the tools?
So today, our health care system
has pretty strong protections
for biospecimens, your blood,
your stool, your genomic data.
But we really don't
have any protections
around digital specimens.
You can imagine how many data
breaches we constantly have
and what ads get served
to us on Facebook.
A lot of this is considered
wellness data, not actually
health data.
But in many instances,
you are finding
quite a lot of
health information
from somebody in that.
And I have a lot more.
We can nerd about this forever.
But generally, there's
a couple of things
that are good to know, is
that with most of this data,
you can't really
de-identify it anymore.
Who here thinks I could
de-identify my genome?
You can't, right?
My genome's unique to me.
Maybe you can strip out
personally identifiable
information, but you're not
really going to de-identify it.
I am uniquely identifiable
with 30 seconds of walk data.
So all of this biometric
signatures is pretty specific.
And so there are
some agencies today
who are thinking
about how you might
handle these sorts of tools.
But in the end, there is, I
think, a pretty substantial
gap.
So in general, the FDA is really
focused on safety and efficacy,
and safety is considered
much more of a body safety
and not as a we are very
programmable as humans
in the type of
information that we
see or change type of safety.
So the data that we collect--
FTC could have a
lot of power here,
but they're a much
smaller agency
that isn't as well-resourced.
And there's a couple of
different organizations
that are trying to
think through how
to do rulemaking for
Internet of Things
and how that data is being used.
But generally, in my
opinion, we probably
need some sort of
congressional action
around non-discrimination of
digital specimen data, which
would require a Congress
that could think through,
I think, a really
difficult problem
of how you would handle
data rights and management.
OK.
So I'll go through
a couple examples
of how government
agencies are interacting
with members of the
public, which I think
you might find interesting.
So, many of the
government agencies
are really thinking through,
realizing that they are not
necessarily the
experts in their field
in how do they get the
data that they need.
So a couple pieces that will be
interesting for you, I think.
One is there is a joint
group with the FDA and Duke,
where they're thinking through
what's called novel endpoints.
So if you are working
on a study today
where you realize that you're
measuring something better
than the quote gold standard,
and the gold standard is
actually quite a
terrible gold standard,
how do you create and
develop a novel metric
that might not have a reference
standard or a legacy standard?
And this is a way of
thinking through that.
The second is around
selecting a mobile technology.
This used to be
called mobile devices,
and they changed it
for the same reason
around not calling things a
device unless it is a device.
And so these are
thinking through what
type of connected
tech would you want
to use to generate the
patient data that you
might use in your study.
All right.
Who here knows what DEFCON is?
Three of you.
OK.
So DEFCON is a
hacker conference.
It is probably one of the
biggest hacker conferences.
It is a conference that if you
do have the joy of going to,
you should not bring your
phone and you should not
bring your computer, and
you should definitely not
connect to the internet
because there is a group called
the Wall of Sheep, and they
will just straight stream
all your Gmail passwords
plain text and your account
logins and anything that you
are putting on the internet.
This group is amazing.
You may have also heard
about them because they
bought a number of voting
machines last year,
hacked them, found
the voting records,
and sent them back to
Congress and said, hey,
you should probably fix this.
DEFCON has a number of villages
that sit under the main DEFCON.
One of them is called
Biohacking Village.
And there is some
biohacking, so,
like, doing the RFID
chipping, citizen science.
But there's also a set of people
at Biohacking Village that
do what's called
white hat hacking.
So for people who
know about this,
there's black cat,
where you might
encrypt somebody's website
and then hold them for ransom
and do things that
are disruptive.
White hat hackers are
considered ethical hackers,
where they are doing security
research on a product.
So the hackers in the
Biohacking Village
started to do a lot of
work on pacemakers, which
are connected technologies.
A lot of pacemaker companies--
an easy way to think about how
they're thinking about this
was the pacemaker companies
are generally trying
to optimize for battery life.
They don't want to
do anything that's
computationally expensive.
Turns out, encrypting things
is computationally expensive.
They did a relatively
trivial exploit
where they were able to
reverse engineer the protocol.
Pacemakers stay in a low power
mode as long as they can.
If you ping it, it will
turn into high power mode,
so you can drain a multi-year
battery of the pacemaker
into a couple days or weeks.
They were also able
to reverse engineer
the shock that a pacemaker can
deliver upon a cardiac event.
And so this has pretty
significant implications
for what this exploit can do.
With any normal
tech company, when
you have an exploit of this
type, you can go to Facebook,
you can go to Amazon,
there is something
called a coordinated disclosure,
you might have a bug bounty,
and then you share the update,
you can submit the update,
and then you're done.
With the device companies,
what was generally
happening is the researchers
were going to the device
companies, hey, we
found this exploit,
and the device companies
were saying, thank you,
we are going to sue you now.
And the security
researchers were
like, why are you suing us?
And they said, you're
tampering with our product,
we are regulated by
agencies, we can't just
ship updates whenever we want,
and so we have to sue you.
Turns out that is not true.
And the FDA found out about
this and they're like,
you can't just do
security researchers.
If you have a security
issue, you have to fix that.
And so the FDA did something
that was pretty bold,
which was three years
ago, they went to DEFCON.
And if anyone has
actually gone to DEFCON,
you would know
that you do not go
to DEFCON if you are
part of the government
because there is a game
called Find the Fed,
and you do not want to be found.
And of course, NSA, CIA, a lot
of members of the government
will go to DEFCON,
but it is generally
not a particularly
friendly environment.
The Biohacking Village said,
hey, we will protect you,
we will give you a
speaker slot, we really
want to work together with you.
And so over the
last three years,
the agency has been
working closely
with security researchers
to really think
through the best ways
of doing cybersecurity,
particularly for
connected devices.
And so if you look at the
past couple of guidances,
there's a premarket and
post-market guidance
where they've been
collaborating,
and they're very good
and strong guidances.
So the FDA did something
really interesting,
which was in January,
they announced
a new initiative, which
I think is quite amazing,
called #WeHeartHackers.
And if you go to
WeHeartHackers.org,
the FDA has been encouraging
device manufacturers,
like Medtronic and BD,
and Philips, and Thermo
Fisher and others, to
bring their devices
and work together with
security researchers.
Another group that is
probably worth knowing
is that if you think
about what a lot
of these connected products
do, they, in many instances,
might augment or change the
way that a clinician does
their work.
And so today, if
you are a clinician
and you graduate
from med school,
you would take something like a
Hippocratic oath to do no harm.
Should the software engineers
and the manufacturers
of these products also take
some sort of oath to do no harm?
And would that oath look
similar or different?
And that line of
thinking helped people
realize that there are entire
professional communities
and societies for people
who do this sort of thing
for doctors in
their specialties,
so a society for neuro
oncology, society for radiology.
But there's really
no society for people
who practice digital medicine.
So there is a group that is
starting now, which you all
might like to join because
I think you would all
be part of this
type of community,
which is the society for--
it's called the DIME Society.
And so if you're
thinking through,
how do I do informed
consent with these sorts
of digital products,
what are the new ways
that I need to think
through regulation,
how am I going to
work with my IRB,
this society could be
a resource for you.
All right.
So how do you participate
in the rulemaking process?
One is, I would
highly encourage,
if you get a chance to, to
serve some time in government.
There are more opportunities to
do that through organizations
like the Presidential
Innovation Fellow,
to be an entrepreneur
resident somewhere,
to be part of the
US Digital Service.
The payment system of CMS is
millions of line of COBOL,
and so that obviously
needs some fixing.
And so if you want
to do a service,
I think this is a
really important way.
Another way that
you can do it is
submitting to a public docket.
And so this is something I
will be asking you to do,
and we'll talk about it
after, is how can you
take what you learned in
that white paper and ways
that you can share back with the
agency of how you would think
about developing rules and laws
around AI and machine learning.
There's a much longer resource
that you can look at, my friend
Mina wrote, which is that--
these are a couple
of things to know.
So anyone can comment,
you will be heard.
If you write a very long
comment, someone at the agency,
probably multiple, will have
to read every single thing
that you write, so please be
judicious in how you do that.
But you will be heard.
And most of the time comments
come from big organizations
and people who have
come together and not
from the people who are
experiencing and using
a lot of the products.
So in my opinion,
I think someone
like you is a really
important comment and voice
for the agency to have, and to
have a technical perspective.
Another way that you
can do this, which
I'm going to put Irene
on the spot, is we
need new regulatory paradigms.
And so when you are out
at beers or ice cream,
or whatever you do for fun, you
can think through new models.
And so we were kicking
around an idea of,
could you use a
clinical trial framework
to think about AI in general?
So algorithms
perform differently
on different patient populations
and different groups.
You need inclusion/exclusion
criteria.
Should this be
something maybe we even
expand beyond health
care algorithms
to how you decide whether or
not someone gets bail or teacher
benefits?
And then the fun thing about
putting your ideas online,
if you do that, is then
people start coming to you.
And we realized there
was a group in Italy who
had proposed a version
of FDA for algorithms,
and you start to
collect people who
are thinking about things
that you're thinking about.
And now we will
dig into the thing
that you most likely
will spend more time
with than the government,
which is your IRB.
MARK SHERVEY: Thank you.
OK.
I could probably not give
the rest of this talk
if you just follow the
thing on the bottom.
If you don't know if you're
doing human subject research,
ask the IRB, ask your
professor, ask somebody.
I think most of what
I'm going to say
is going to be a lot softer,
squishier than what Andy went
around, and it's
really just to try
to get the thought process going
through your head of if we're
doing actual human research,
if the IRB has to be involved,
what actually constitutes
human research?
And just to be sure that
you're aware of what's
going on there all the time.
We've done this.
So research is
systematic investigation
to develop or contribute
generalizable knowledge.
So you can do that on a rock.
What's important
about human subjects
research is that people's
lives are on the line.
Generally, the
easiest thing to know
is if there's any sort of
identifiable information
with the data that
you're working with,
that is going to fall under
human subjects research.
Things that won't are publicly
available, anonymous data.
There's all sorts of
imaging training data
sets that you can use
that are anonymized
to what is an acceptable level.
But to Andy's point,
there's really
no way to truly
de-identify a data set.
And with the amount of data that
we're working with all right
now in the world, it's
becoming impossible
to de-identify any data set if
you have any other reference
data set.
So anytime you're
working with any people,
you are almost
certainly going to have
to involve the IRB, again.
So why the IRB is there,
it's not specifically
to slap you on the wrists.
It's not that
anything's expected
to purposely do anything wrong.
Although that has happened,
that's such a small amount
that it's just
unhelpful to think
that everybody is malicious.
So you're not going to do
anything particularly wrong,
but there are things that
you just may not know.
And this is not the
IRB's 1,000th rodeo,
so if you bring
something up to them,
they'll know almost immediately.
Participants are giving up
their time and information,
so the IRB, more than keeping
the institution from harm,
is really protecting
the patients
first and the institution
at the same time.
But the main role is to
protect the participants.
Specifically, here's
something that might not
go through everybody's
head, research
that may be questionable
or overly manipulative.
That gets into
compensation for studies.
You can imagine certain places
in an impoverished nation
that you say, we'll
pay $50,000 per person
to come participate
in this study,
you can imagine people
want to be in that study
and it can become a problem.
So the IRB is also a
huge part of making sure
that the studies aren't actually
affecting anybody negatively
in that kind of sense.
Now, before I do, this next
slide gets dark for a second,
so we'll try to move through it.
But it talks about how
the IRB came about.
So we start with the Nuremberg
Code, human research conducted
on prisoners and
others, not participants
but subjects of research.
Tuskegee experiment,
another thing
that people were not properly
consented into the studies.
They didn't know what they
were actually being tested for,
so they couldn't
possibly have consented.
The study went for 40 years
instead of six months.
And even after a standard of
care had been established,
the study continued on.
That essentially is what
began the National Commission
for Protection of Human
Subjects, which led to the IRB
being the requirement
for research.
And then five years
later, the Belmont Report
came out, essentially
enumerating
these three basic principles,
respect for participants,
beneficence as far as
do no harm, don't take
extra blood if it just
makes it more convenient,
don't add extra drug if you
just want to see what happens,
and then just making
sure that participants
are safe outside of any
other harm that you can do.
So we follow the Belmont Report.
That's essentially
the state of the art
that we have now with
modernization moving forward.
This is not something
to really worry about,
but HHS has a
great site that has
a flow chart for just about any
circumstance that you can think
of to decide if you're actually
doing human subjects research
or not.
This is pretty much
the most basic one.
You can go through
it on your own.
Just to highlight the main thing
that I think you guys will all
probably be worried
about, is you
will be collecting identifiable
data, which just immediately
puts you in IRB land.
So anytime you can
identify that that's
a thing that's happening,
you're just there,
so you don't really have
to go through any of this.
What is health data?
So you have names obviously.
Most of these are either
identifications or some sort
of identifying thing.
The two, I guess,
that a lot of people
maybe gloss over that aren't
so obvious is zip codes.
You have to limit them to the
first three numbers of a zip
code, which gives a
generalizable area
without actually dialing
in on a person's place.
Dates are an extremely
sensitive topic.
So anytime you're working
with actual dates, which
I assume in wearable
technologies
you're going to be
dealing with time series
data and that kind of stuff.
There are different ways of
making that less sensitive.
But anytime you're dealing
with research, anytime
we're dealing with the
electronic health records,
we deal in years, not in
actual dates, which can--
it creates problems
if you are trying
to do time series analysis
for somebody's entire health
record, in which case you can
get further clearance to work
with more identifiable data.
But that is progressive
as it can be.
There's no reason to start with
that kind of data if you don't.
So it's always on
a need to know.
Finally, if you're working
with patients older than 90,
90 or older, they are just
generalized as a category
of greater than 90.
The rest of these, I think,
are fairly guessable,
so we don't have
to go through them.
But those are the tricky ones
that some people don't catch.
Again, just limit the collection
of PHI as strictly as possible.
If you don't need
it, don't get it.
If you're sharing
the data, instead
of sharing an entire data set
if you do have strong PHI,
limit what you're giving or
sharing to another researcher.
That's just a hygiene
issue, and it's really
limiting the amount of
errors that can happen.
So why is this so important?
The IRB, again, is particularly
interested in protecting
patients and making
sure that there's
as little harm, if any, done
as possible to patients.
Just general human
decency and respect.
There's institutional
risk if something
is done without an
IRB, and you can't
publish if you have
done human subjects
research without an IRB.
Those two are kind of the
stick, but the carrot really
should be the top two, as
far as just human decency
and making sure that
you've protected
any patients or any
participants that you
have involved in your research.
These are a couple
of violations.
We don't have to
get too far into it,
but they were both
allegedly conducted
without any IRB approval.
There's possible
fraud involved, and it
ruined both of their careers.
But it put people
at huge exposures
to unhealthy conditions.
This is probably a much
bigger common issue
that you're going to have.
PHI data breaches,
they happen a lot.
They're generally not
breaches from the outside.
They're accidents.
Somebody will set
up a web server
on the machine serving PHI
because they found it easier
to work at home one day.
It could just be they don't
know how software is set up.
So anytime you're
working with PHI,
you've really got to overdo it
on knowing exactly how you're
working with it.
Other breaches are losing
unencrypted computers,
putting data on a thumb
drive and losing it.
The gross amount
of data breaches
happen just from
negligence and not
being as careful
as you want to be.
So that's always
good to keep in mind.
I guess a new thing with
the IRB and digital research
is things have been changing now
from face to face recruitment
and research into being
able to consent online
to be able to reach millions
of people across the world
and allowing them to
consent on their own.
So this has become, obviously,
a new thing since the Belmont
Report, and it's something
that we are working closely
with our IRB to make sure that
we're being as respectful as we
can to the patients,
but also making sure
that we can develop
software solutions that
are not hurting anybody and
develop into swim lanes.
So what we've come up with a
framework for is that there's
a project which is--
we're studying all cancers.
So you can post reports about
different research that's going
on, things that seem important.
A study is an
actual person that's
consented to a protocol,
which is human research
and subject to IRB.
Then we'll have a platform
that the users will use,
and that will be like a
website or an iPhone app
that they can get literature
information about what
the project is going on.
And then we'll have a
participant who is actually
part of a study, who's,
again, covered under IRB
through consent.
So why this kind of
development has been important,
the old way of
software development
was the waterfall approach,
where you work for three weeks,
implement something,
work for three weeks,
implement something, where we
have moved to a Agile approach
in software.
And so while Agile makes our
lives a lot easier as far
as development, we
can't be sure what
we're doing isn't going
to affect patients
in certain contexts.
So within a study, working
Agile makes no sense.
We have we want to work with
the IRB to approve things,
but IRB approval takes
between two and four
weeks for expedited things.
When we talk about
projects and stuff,
that's where we want to work
safely in an Agile environment
and try to figure out
places where the IRB doesn't
necessarily have to be involved
or doesn't want to be involved
and that there isn't
any added patient risk
whatsoever in working in
that kind of environment.
So it's working with software
products versus studies,
and so working with
the IRB to be sure
that we can separate
those things
and make sure that
things move on
as well as possible
without any added harm.
So that's these
categories again.
So project activity would
be social media outreach,
sharing content that is relevant
to the project and kind of just
informing about a general idea.
A study activity is
what you would generally
be used to with
consent, data sharing,
actually participating
in a study,
whether it's through a wearable,
answering questions, and then
withdrawing in the process.
And the study
activities are 100% IRB,
where the project activities
that aren't directly
dealing with the
study can hopefully
be separated in most cases.
So the three takeaways really
are just if you don't know,
ask, limit the collection of
PHI as strictly as possible,
and working in Agile
developments are great but it
is unsafe in a lot
of human research,
so we have to focus on where
that can be used and where it
can't.
And that's it.
Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]
Oh.
AUDIENCE: I have a question
about how it's actually done.
So as the IRB, how
do you make sure
that your researcher
is complying?
Is that, like, writing
a report, doing a PDF,
or is there a third
party service?
MARK SHERVEY: Yeah, yeah.
So we certify all
of our researchers
with human research and HIPAA
compliance, just blanket.
And if you provide that and your
certifications are up to date,
it's an understanding
that the researcher
knows what they should
be looking out for
and that the IRB understands.
AUDIENCE: So is
that a third party?
MARK SHERVEY: Oh, yeah, yeah.
We use a third party.
You can have--
I don't-- we use a third party.
PROFESSOR: Can I just add--
MARK SHERVEY: Oh, yeah.
PROFESSOR: So at MIT,
there's something
called COUHES, the
Committee on Use
of Humans as
Experimental Subjects,
and they are our official IRB.
It used to be all paper.
Now there's an electronic
way where you can
apply for a COUHES protocol.
And it's a reasonably
long document
in which you describe the
purpose of the experiment, what
you're going to do,
what kind of people
you're going to recruit, what
recruiting material you're
going to use, how you
will handle the data,
what security
provisions you have.
Of course, if you're
doing something
like injecting
people with toxins,
then that's a much more
serious kind of thing,
and you have to describe the
preliminary data on why you
think this is safe and so on.
And that gets reviewed
at, essentially,
one of three levels.
There is exempt
review, which is--
you can't exempt yourself,
but they can exempt you.
And what they would say
is, this is a minimal risk
kind of problem.
So let's say you're doing a data
only study using mimic data,
and you've done
the city training,
you've signed the
data use agreement.
You're supposed to get
IRB permission for it.
There is an exception
for students
in a classroom, in which
case I'm responsible rather
than making you responsible.
But if you screw it
up, I'm responsible.
The second level is
an expedited approval,
which is a low risk
kind of approval,
typically data only studies.
But it may involve things
like using limited data sets,
where, for example,
if you're trying
to study the geographical
distribution of disease,
then you clearly need better
geographical identifiers
than a three-digit
zip code, or if you're
trying to study a time series,
as Mark was talking about,
you need actual dates.
And so you can get approval
to use that kind of data.
And then there's
the full on review,
which takes much longer,
where they do actually
bring in people to
evaluate the safety of what
you're proposing to do.
So far, my experience
is that mostly
with the kinds of
studies that we
do that are representative of
the material we're studying
in class, we don't have to
get into that third category
because we're not actually
doing anything that
is likely to harm
individual patients,
except in a kind of reputational
or data-oriented sense,
and that doesn't require
the full blown review.
So that's the local situation.
MARK SHERVEY: Yeah, thank you.
Yeah, I think I misunderstood
the full range of the question.
Yeah, and that's
roughly our same thing.
So we have--
Eddie Golden is our
research project manager,
who is my favorite person in the
office for this kind of stuff.
She keeps on top of
everything and makes
sure that the right people
are listed on research
and that people are taken
off, that kind of stuff.
But it's a good
relationship with the IRB
on that kind of stuff.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: So I'm somewhat
unfamiliar with Agile software
development practices.
On a high level, it's
just more parallelized
and we update more frequently?
MARK SHERVEY: Yeah, yeah.
I don't know if I
took that slide out,
but there's something
where Amazon
will deploy 50 million
updates per year or something
like that.
So it's constantly on
an update frequency
instead of just building
everything up and then dropping
it.
And that's just been a new
development in software.
AUDIENCE: Can we ask
questions to both you guys?
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: Can you tell us
more about Elektra Labs?
I couldn't fully understand.
Are you guys more consultantancy
for all these, we'll call them,
tool companies?
Or is it more like a
lobbying kind of thing?
The reason I ask this is
also because I wonder what
your opinion is on a third
party source for determining
whether these things are a
good or bad kind of thing
because it seems
like the FDA would
have trouble understanding.
So if you had some organic
certified kind of thing,
would that be a useful solution?
Or where does that go wrong?
ANDY CORAVOS: Mm-hm, yeah.
So what we're
building with Elektra
is effectively a pharmacy
for connecting technologies.
So the way that today
you have pharmacies
that have a formulary of
all the different drugs that
are available,
this is effectively
like a digital pharmacy,
like a Kelley Blue Book
of all the different tools.
And then we're building out
a label for each of them
based on as much
objective data as we can,
so that we're not
scoring whether or not
something's good or bad.
Because in most
instances, things
aren't good or bad
and absolute, they're
good or bad for a purpose.
And so you can imagine
something-- maybe
you need really high
levels of accuracy,
so you need to
know whether or not
that tool has been
verified and validated
in certain contexts in
certain patient populations.
Even if the tool's
accurate, if you're
to recharge it all the
time or you can't wear it
in the shower, you won't have
the usability, or if the APIs
are really hard to work with.
And then security profile,
whether or not they
have coordinated disclosure,
how they handle things
like the tool companies, like
a software bill of materials
and what kind of
software is used.
And then even if the
tool is accurate,
even if it's relatively
usable, even if it's secure,
that doesn't solve the
Cambridge Analytica problem,
so how tools are doing
a third party transfer.
And so one of the philosophies
is we don't score,
but we are building
out the data set
so when you are
evaluating a certain tool,
it's like a nutrition label.
Sometimes you need
more sugar, sometimes
you need more protein.
Maybe you need more
security, maybe
you really need to think
about the data rates.
Maybe you can take a leave on
some of the accuracy levels.
And so we're all
building out this ability
to evaluate the tools, and
then also to deploy them
like the way that a pharmacy
would deploy them out.
One thing I would like
to do with the group,
if you all are down for
it, out of civic duty--
and I'm serious, though.
Voting is very important
and submitting your comments
to the public register
is very important.
And I read all your comments
because Irene sent them to me,
and they were very good.
And I know probably
people who came
here want to polish everything
and make them perfect.
You can submit them
exactly how they are.
And I am very much hoping
that we get about 95%
of you to submit, and
the 5% of you that
didn't, like, your internet
broke or something.
You can submit tonight.
I will email Irene because you
already have done the work,
and you can submit it.
But I would like to just
hear some of your thoughts.
So what I'm going
to do is I'm going
to use that same framework
around, what would you keep?
What would you change?
And then change can
also include, like,
what was so confusing in
there, that it didn't even
really make sense?
Part of the confusion
might be that it was--
some regulations are confusing.
But some of the confusion is
that part of that document
was not written by people who--
some people have technical
backgrounds and some do not.
And so sometimes
some of the language
might not actually
be used in the way
that industry is using it
today, so refining the language.
And then what did you
see that was missing?
So here's what
we're going to do.
Keep, change slash confusing,
and then start or add.
And before I ask you,
I want you to look
at the person next
to you, seriously,
and if there's three
of you, that's fine,
and I want you to
tell them when you
will be submitting the comment.
Is it tonight, tomorrow,
or you are choosing not to?
Just look at them and talk.
[INDISTINCT CHATTER]
There will be a link.
I will send you all links.
I will make this very easy.
OK.
All right.
Who wants to start?
We got three things
on the board.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So one thing that--
I don't know if this is
confusing or just intentionally
vague, but for things like
quality systems and machine
learning practices, who
sets those standards
and how can they be
adapted or changed?
ANDY CORAVOS: Mm-hm.
I don't also know
that answer, and so I
would like you to submit--
one of the things
that is nice is then
that you have to respond, yeah.
And I think it's also
a little bit confusing,
even the language.
So people are using
different things.
People call it GXP, good
manufacturing practice,
good clinical practice.
These are maintained, I
think, in some instances
by different orgs.
I wonder if good algorithm
practice gap or good machine
learning practice--
yeah, that's a good thing.
So who owns GXP?
OK.
Yes?
You didn't have a question?
No.
AUDIENCE: Just wanted
to share something.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yes.
AUDIENCE: One of the things
I found really to keep
were the examples
in the appendix.
I don't know [INAUDIBLE].
--general guidelines,
and so it's
more that the language
itself is more generalized
and so the examples are
really hopeful for what
is a specific situation
that's analogous to make.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yep.
Like that?
Yeah, examples are helpful.
Yep?
AUDIENCE: Speaking of specifics,
I thought around transparency
they could have been
much more specific
and that we should generally
adhere to guidelines as opposed
to the exact set
of data that is--
this algorithm is exactly
what's coming out of it,
the exact quality
metrics, things
like that that hold people
accountable as opposed to there
are many instances to
not be transparent.
And so if those
aren't as specific,
I worry that not that much
really would happen there.
The analog like I
thought of was when
Facebook asks for
your data, they
say here are the things that
we need or that we're using,
and it's very explicit.
And then you can have a
choice of whether or not
you actually want that.
ANDY CORAVOS: OK.
AUDIENCE: So seeing something
like that [INAUDIBLE]..
ANDY CORAVOS: So part
of it is transparency,
but also user choice
in data selection or--
AUDIENCE: Yeah, I think
that was, for me, more
of an analog because choice
in the medical setting
is a bit more complex.
Someone who doesn't
have the ability
in that case or the knowledge
to actually make that choice.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
AUDIENCE: I think at
the very least saying
this algorithm is using this,
and maybe some sort of choice.
So you can work with
someone, and maybe there's
some parameters around
what you would or would not
have that choice.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yep.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: What if you added
something about algorithm bias?
Because I know that that's
been relevant for a lot
of other industries
in terms of confidence
within the legal
system, and then also
in terms of facial recognition
not working fully across races.
So I think that breaking
things down by population
and ensuring equitable
across different populations
is important.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yep.
I don't know if I slept
enough, so if I just
gave this example-- but a friend
of mine called me last week
and asked for PPGs, so
the sensor on the back.
She was asking me if it
works on all skin colors
and whether or not it
responds differently.
And if it responds
differently, whether or not
somebody has a tattoo.
And so for some of the
big registries that
are doing bring your
own device data,
you can have unintended
biases in the data sets
just because of how
that it's processing.
So yeah.
What do you think?
What are ways--
I think Irene's worked
with some of this.
How do you think
about whether or not
something is-- what would be
a good system for the agency
to consider around bias?
AUDIENCE: I think maybe
coming into consideration
with [INAUDIBLE] system
might be part of the GNLP.
But I think it would be the
responsibility of the designer
to assess [INAUDIBLE].
ANDY CORAVOS: OK.
AUDIENCE: As a
note, bearing this
is our next lecture, so anyone
who might be confused or want
to talk about it more, we will
have plenty material next time.
ANDY CORAVOS: You
want to pick someone?
MARK SHERVEY: I'm sorry.
Go ahead.
AUDIENCE: Me?
MARK SHERVEY: Yeah.
ANDY CORAVOS: Cold call.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Just adding off at
another place, so it looked
like there was a
period for providing
periodic reportings to the
FDA on updates and all that.
There could also
be like a scorecard
of bias on subpopulations
or something to that effect.
ANDY CORAVOS: Mm-hm.
That's cool.
Have you seen any places
that do something like that?
AUDIENCE: I remember when I
read Weapons of Math Destruction
from Cathy O'Neil, she mentioned
some sort of famous audit.
But I don't really
remember the details.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
When you do submit your comment,
if you have ideas or links,
or it can be posts
or blogs or whatever,
just link them in because
one thing that you'll find
is that we read a lot
of things, probably
the same things on Twitter, but
other groups don't necessarily
see all of that.
So I think that Cathy O'Neil
is really interesting work,
but yeah, just tag stuff.
It doesn't have to be
formatted amazingly.
PROFESSOR: So in some
of the communities
that I follow, not on Twitter
but email and on the web,
there's been a lot of discussion
about really terrible design
of information
systems in hospitals
and how these lead to errors.
Now, I know from
your slide, Andy,
that the FDA has defined those
to be out of its purview.
But it seems to me
that there's probably,
at the moment, more harm
being done by information
systems that encourage
really bad practice
or that allow bad
practice than there
is by retinopathy,
AI, machine learning
techniques that make mistakes.
So just this morning,
for example, somebody
posted a message
about a patient who
had a heart rate of 12,000,
which seems extremely unlikely.
[LAUGHTER]
ANDY CORAVOS: Yep.
PROFESSOR: And the
problem is that when
you start automating
processes that
are based on the information
that is collected
in these systems, things
can go really screwy when
you get garbage data.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
Have you thought about
that with your system?
MARK SHERVEY: We
cannot get good data.
I mean, you're not going to get
good data out of those systems.
What you're seeing
is across the board,
and there's not much
you can do about
it other than validate good
ranges and go from there.
PROFESSOR: Well, I can
think of things to do.
For example, if FDA were
interested in regulating
such devices--
oh, sorry, such tools--
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
Well, they would
regulate devices.
So one of the funny
things with FDA is--
and I should have
mentioned this--
is the FDA does not regulate
the practice of medicine.
So doctors can do
whatever they want.
They regulate-- well,
you should look up
exactly-- the way I interpret it
is they regulate the marketing
that a manufacturer would do.
So I actually wonder if the EHRs
would be considered practice
of medicine or if it would be a
marketing from the EHR company,
and maybe that's how it
could be under their purview.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: I guess
something that I
was surprised not
to see as much about
were privacy issues in this.
I know there's ways where you
can train machine learning
models and extract information
that the data was trained on.
At least I'm pretty
sure that exists.
It's not my expertise.
But I was wondering if anything
like that [INAUDIBLE] have
someone try to extract
the data that you can't.
But you talked about that a lot
in your section of the talk,
but I don't remember
it as much [INAUDIBLE]..
ANDY CORAVOS: OK.
Yep.
Realistically,
how many of you do
think you'll actually
submit a comment?
A couple.
So if you're thinking you
wouldn't submit a comment, just
out of curiosity, I
won't argue with you,
I'm just curious, what
would hold you back
from submitting a comment?
If you didn't raise your hand
now, I get to cold call you.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: I raised
my hand before.
We were just talking.
Most of us have our
computers open now.
If you really want us to submit
it as is, if you put it up,
we could all submit.
ANDY CORAVOS: OK.
OK, OK.
Wow.
AUDIENCE: We are
95% [INAUDIBLE]..
ANDY CORAVOS: All right.
PROFESSOR: So while
Andy is looking that up,
I should say when the HIPAA
regulations, the privacy
regulations were first proposed,
the initial version got 70,000
public comments about it.
And it is really true that
the regulatory agency,
in that case, it was
Health and Human Services,
had to respond to every
one of those by law.
And so they published
reams of paper
about responding to
all those requests.
So they will take your comments
seriously because they have to.
AUDIENCE: I was going to say,
is there any way of anonymously
commenting?
Or does it have to be tied
to us, out of curiosity?
ANDY CORAVOS: I don't know.
I think it's generally--
I don't know, I'd have
to look at it again.
I think most of them
are public comments.
I mean, I guess
if you wanted to,
maybe you could coordinate
your comments and you could--
yeah, OK.
Irene is willing
to group comment.
So you can also send if
you'd like to do it that way,
and it can be a set of class
comments, if you would prefer.
The Bitly is capital MIT all
lowercase loves FDA, will
send you over to the docket.
I'm amazed that that Bitly
has not been taken already.
PROFESSOR: [INAUDIBLE] has
been asleep on the job.
ANDY CORAVOS: What other
questions do you all have?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: So what is the line
between an EHR and a SaMD?
Because it said it earlier
that EHR is exempted,
but then it also says, oh,
for example, with SaMD,
it could be collecting
physiological signals,
and then they might
send an audible alarm
to indicate [INAUDIBLE].
And my understanding is
some of EHRs do that.
ANDY CORAVOS: Mm-hm.
AUDIENCE: And so would they need
to be retroactively approved
and partially SaMD-ified?
Or how's that work?
ANDY CORAVOS: So
I'm not a regulator,
so you should ask
your regulator.
A couple resources that could
help you decide this is,
again, it's about what you're
claiming the product does,
perhaps not what
it actually does.
The next thing,
which I don't think--
I mean, I think if it really
does that, you should also
claim that it does what
it does, especially
if it's confusing for people.
There's a couple of regulations
that might be helpful.
One is called Clinical
Decision Support.
And if you read any FDA things,
they love their algorithms--
I mean, they love
their algorithms,
but they also love
their acronyms.
So Clinical Decision Support
is CDS, and then also
Patient Decision Support.
There's a guidance
that just came out
around the two types of
decision support tools,
and I would guess maybe
that is supporting
a decision, that EHR.
So it might actually
be considered something
that would be regulated.
There's also a lot of weird--
we didn't go into it, but
there are many instances
where something might
actually be a device
and the FDA says it's a device,
but it will do something called
enforcement discretion,
which says it's a device
but we will not
regulate it as such.
Which is actually a little
bit risky for a manufacturer
because you are device, but you
can now go straight to market.
In some instances, you still
have to register and list
the product, but you don't have
to necessarily get reviewed.
And it also could
eventually be reviewed.
So the line of, is it a
device, is it a device
and you have to
register, is it a device
and you have to get
cleared or approved,
is why you should
early and often--
yes?
AUDIENCE: I enjoyed
your game with regards
to Fitbit and Apple.
And I have a question
about the app.
I know that you're
not Apple either,
but why do you think that Apple
went for FDA approval versus
Fitbit who didn't?
What were the motivations
for the companies to do that?
ANDY CORAVOS: I would
say, in public documents,
Fitbit has expressed an interest
in working with the FDA.
I don't know at what point
they have decided what they
submitted or had their package.
They're also working with
the pre-cert program.
So I don't know what's
happening behind the scenes.
Yeah?
AUDIENCE: Does it give them
a business edge, perhaps,
to get FDA approval?
ANDY CORAVOS: I cannot
comment on that.
AUDIENCE: OK, no worries.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
I would say,
generally, people want
to use tools that
are trustworthy,
and developing more tools
that have somebody of evidence
is a really important thing.
I think the FDA is one
way of having evidence.
I think there are other ways
that tools and devices can
continue to build evidence.
My hope is over time, that a
lot of these things that we
consider to be wellness tools
also have evidence around them.
Maybe in some instances we
don't always regulate vitamins,
but you want to still trust
that your vitamin doesn't
have sawdust in it, right,
and that it's a real product.
And so the more
that we, I think,
push companies to have
evidence and that we
use products that do that, I
hope over time this helps us.
PROFESSOR: Does it give
them any legal protection
to have it be classified
as an FDA device?
ANDY CORAVOS: I'm
not sure about that.
Historically, it has
helped with reimbursement.
So a class two product has
been easier to reimburse.
That also is generally
changing, but that
helps with the business
model around that.
PROFESSOR: Yeah.
Well, I want to thank
you both very much.
That was really interesting.
And I do encourage all
of you to participate
in this regulatory process
by submitting your comments.
And I enjoyed the presentations.
Thank you.
ANDY CORAVOS: Yeah.
MARK SHERVEY: Thank you.
ANDY CORAVOS: Thank you.
[APPLAUSE]